<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Django | Scott Domes | Web Developer]]></title>
  <link href="http://scottdomes.com/blog/categories/django/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://scottdomes.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-25T11:12:44-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://scottdomes.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Scott Domes]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Create a Django API in Under 20 Minutes]]></title>
    <link href="http://scottdomes.com/blog/create-a-django-api-in-under-20-minutes/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-11T16:51:01-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://scottdomes.com/blog/create-a-django-api-in-under-20-minutes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Django is by far the most popular Python framework, designed to provide
Rails-like ease of use. Let’s see how quickly we can set up a simple API using
Django and a library called TastyPie.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*cGZQTle3SrxD9STT9LuuMQ.png" alt="" /></p>

<!--more-->


<p>For those of you who read the <a href="https://medium.com/@scottdomes/building-a-simple-node-js-api-in-under-30-minutes-a07ea9e390d2#.mov6a516k">Node API
tutorial</a>,
we’re now going to attempt to do the same thing with Django. We’ll also very
quickly see how Django makes some things harder, and some things much much
easier.</p>

<p><strong>Who This Tutorial Is For</strong>: You should have a basic understanding of REST APIs
and CRUD operations. Python knowledge is a plus but not necessary. You’ll pick
it up.</p>

<p>We’ll be building an API for a Google Keep-esque note-taking web app. We want to
build a REST-ful API with the CRUD endpoints, to create, read, update, and
delete notes. The good news is that rather than approach these endpoints
individually, Django lets us more or less create them all in one fell swoop.</p>

<h3><strong>Setting Up Our Project</strong></h3>

<p>Django divides your work into projects and apps. Projects contain apps, but apps
do not necessarily belong to a certain project — the idea is to make them
reusable across projects.</p>

<p>We’ll only be making one app within one project, but the file structure may seem
a little odd if you don’t keep this in mind.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.python.org/downloads/">Install Python</a> if you haven’t done so, then
let’s install Django and create our project:
<code>
    pip install Django
    django-admin startproject notable_django
    cd notable_django
</code>
Next we’ll install
<a href="https://github.com/django-tastypie/django-tastypie">TastyPie</a>, which will
supply us with a REST framework.
<code>
    pip install django-tastypie
</code>
Finally, we can start our app within our project:
<code>
    python manage.py startapp api
</code>
Within your notable_django directory, you should now have two subfolders: one
also called notable_django, and another named api (as well as a manage.py file).</p>

<p>The distinction between the two can be thought of like this: the notable_django
contains the settings for the configuration of the project, as well as exposing
URLs. The api folder handles the actual API magic.</p>

<p>Before we go on, we have to install our app within our project, inside
notable_django/settings-py:
``` python
    # notable_django/settings.py</p>

<pre><code>INSTALLED_APPS = [
    'django.contrib.admin',
    'django.contrib.auth',
    'django.contrib.contenttypes',
    'django.contrib.sessions',
    'django.contrib.messages',
    'django.contrib.staticfiles',
]
</code></pre>

<pre><code>Again, our project can have multiple apps installed — and those apps aren’t
necessarily tied to that project. Our project here is notable_django, and our
app is called api.

With that done, we’re ready to start building.

### A Model Start

The first thing we need to create is a Note model to interact with.

For those unfamiliar with models, [this
description](https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.10/topics/db/models/) from the
Django docs is as good as any:

&gt; A model is the single, definitive source of information about your data. It
&gt; contains the essential fields and behaviors of the data you’re storing.
Generally, each model maps to a single database table.

Django is unique (compared to a framework like Ruby on Rails) in that your
migrations follow how you define your models, rather than being separately
defined.

We’re going to create our Note model, and then run our migrations, which will
set up our database with a notes table (with all the appropriate fields).

Let’s create our model, in api/models.py
</code></pre>

<pre><code># api/models.py

class Note(models.Model):
    title = models.CharField(max_length=200)
    body = models.TextField()
    created_at = models.DateTimeField(auto_now_add=True)
</code></pre>

<pre><code>We define our fields, along with the type of each.

The next thing we want to do is add a __str__ method to the model. This method
defines what we get when we ask for a particular instance of a model.

For example, this:
</code></pre>

<pre><code># api/models.py

class Note(models.Model):
    title = models.CharField(max_length=200)
    body = models.TextField()
    created_at = models.DateTimeField(auto_now_add=True)

def __str__(self):
        return self.title
</code></pre>

<pre><code>… means that when we grab any Note model, we’ll get back only the title. This
just keeps things clean. (We will only be interacting with our models in this
manner through the Python shell, so it’s not super necessary, but good to be
aware of).

Let’s expand our __str__ method to also include the body:
</code></pre>

<pre><code># api/models.py

class Note(models.Model):
    title = models.CharField(max_length=200)
    body = models.TextField()
    created_at = models.DateTimeField(auto_now_add=True)

def __str__(self):
        return '%s %s' % (self.title, self.body)
</code></pre>

<pre><code>Okay, our model is all set up. Now to run our migrations, which will set up our
database.
</code></pre>

<pre><code>python manage.py makemigrations
python manage.py migrate
</code></pre>

<pre><code>Let’s go ahead and populate our database with a single note, to make sure all is
well:
</code></pre>

<pre><code>python manage.py shell
&gt;&gt;&gt; from api.models import Note
&gt;&gt;&gt; note = Note(title="First Note", body="This is certainly noteworthy")
&gt;&gt;&gt; note.save()
&gt;&gt;&gt; Note.objects.all()
&lt;QuerySet [&lt;Note: First Note This is certainly noteworthy&gt;]&gt;
&gt;&gt;&gt; exit()
</code></pre>

<pre><code>We create our note, save it, then retrieve all notes. You can see our __str__
method at work, returning both the title and the body.

(If you want to learn more about the Note.objects manager, [see
here](https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/1.10/topics/db/managers/#django.db.models.Manager)).

### API-ification

Okay, so our model and database are all ready to go. Now to expose some
endpoints to the wider world, so we can interact with our data.

One of the basics of RESTful APIs is the idea of resources. The term is rather
abstract, but in this context it refers to a class that sits between our URLs
and our models.

A user will make a request to an endpoint. Depending on the URL, the user will
be redirected to a particular resource, which will then perform the appropriate
CRUD action on the model.

Again, this is a simplified explanation of a complex topic — let’s go ahead and
see it in practice:

In your api folder, create a new file called *resources.py.*
</code></pre>

<pre><code># api/resources.py

from tastypie.resources import ModelResource
from api.models import Note

class NoteResource(ModelResource):
    class Meta:
        queryset = Note.objects.all()
        resource_name = 'note'
</code></pre>

<pre><code>We import our model, and create a resource from it. The *queryset* (what models
the resource is concerned with) is all note objects.

We also name the resource appropriately: ‘note’. This will be important for
URLs.

Speaking of which, let’s set those up in our notable_django/urls.py file:
</code></pre>

<pre><code>from django.conf.urls import url
from django.contrib import admin


urlpatterns = [
    url(r'^admin/', admin.site.urls),
]
</code></pre>

<pre><code>We import our NoteResource, instantiate it, and then say that we want all URLs
that start with api/ to redirect to the resource. (Don’t forget to import
*include *from django.conf.urls).

### Testing Our API

Finally, we can get running. As in the Node tutorial, we’re going to use Postman
to make API requests. You can get it [here](https://www.getpostman.com/).
</code></pre>

<pre><code>python manage.py runserver
</code></pre>

<pre><code>Now in Postman, let’s send a GET request to this URL:
[http://localhost:8000/api/note/1](http://localhost:8000/api/note/1)

![](https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*8Paypbwf_k8z-csMl2xpVw.png)

Great! Our GET endpoint is working perfectly. Easy.

Now let’s try to create a new note from Postman.

### POST, PUT, DELETE

We’re going to send a raw JSON object as our new note, like so:

![](https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*bbtveT-w_9ji_nfjz9-pMA.png)

Make sure you select JSON from the orange dropdown there! This will set a
Content-Type header (which you can view under the Headers tab).

Also make sure you send the request to
[http://localhost:8000/api/note](http://localhost:8000/api/note/1)/, not
[http://localhost:8000/api/note](http://localhost:8000/api/note/1). That
trailing slash is important, since otherwise Django has to redirect you, losing
the POST data.

Send that request and… it fails. We get back a 401, AKA Unauthorized.

TastyPie is protective of its models out of the box, and only allows reading,
not modifying, the data.

It’s an easy fix, though — import their basic Authorization class, and add it to
our resource.
</code></pre>

<pre><code># api/resources.py

from tastypie.resources import ModelResource
from api.models import Note
from tastypie.authorization import Authorization

class NoteResource(ModelResource):
    class Meta:
        queryset = Note.objects.all()
        resource_name = 'note'
        authorization = Authorization()
</code></pre>

<pre><code>Now it works! Try the request, and we get back 201, AKA success!

To double check, you can send a GET request to
[http://localhost:8000/api/note](http://localhost:8000/api/note/1). You should
get back both notes.

Important warning: the Authorization class with TastyPie is, in their words,
great for development — but not suitable for actual deployment. You can dive
deeper into TastyPie authorization
[here](http://django-tastypie.readthedocs.io/en/latest/authorization.html).

### All the Endpoints

Okay, so we finished our GET and POST endpoints. What about PUT and DELETE?

Well, the magic of TastyPie is that they’re already done. Try updating or
deleting your first note by ending PUT or DELETE to
[http://localhost:8000/api/note/1/](http://localhost:8000/api/note/1/). It just
works!

Just like that, we created a working RESTful API.

### Limiting Fields

If you wanted to only send specific information about a resource, you can limit
fields like so:
</code></pre>

<pre><code>from tastypie.resources import ModelResource
from api.models import Note
from tastypie.authorization import Authorization

class NoteResource(ModelResource):
    class Meta:
        queryset = Note.objects.all()
        resource_name = 'note'
        authorization = Authorization()
        fields = ['title', 'body']
</code></pre>

<p>```
Now you won’t see our created_at field in any requests.</p>

<h3>Final Notes</h3>

<p>Thanks for reading. If this tutorial has been helpful, please share it with your friends and fellow devs.</p>

<p>You can also follow me for more tutorials and guides. And, as always, please
leave any feedback or questions in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
